I think we as a society celebrate
tech companies
far too much versus
the impact of technology.
think about the decades
all of us have spent saying,
can we have one tech intervention
that makes a damn difference in education,
we are definitely trying to build
a scaffolding for the AI age. I'm curious
what you think the world will look like
when 90 or 95% of all code is generated by AI?
Ultimately the human is in the loop,
I think we overstate the autonomy here.
Remember at Microsoft
we are not like there's one trick company.
the hardest thing for us
is being adjusting.
The reality is, case studies don't help.
You have to do it yourself technology
is powerful enough to disappear.
This is something that recently
went viral.
you mentioned
that AGI is just some nonsensical
benchmark hacking,
and the true value of AI is...
All right.
Satya, thanks so much for being here.
So we're just minutes after
you just hopped off the stage at Build.
Can you explain
how all these new developments
really are coming together
to build that new agenetic web?
Yeah. First of all, thanks so much
for being at the developer conference.
And you know, for us,
the it's it's interesting,
you know, when I think about this,
we're at that moment, right?
Whatever.
2 or 3 years into a platform shift,
and you start talking about the platform,
not just about the one app or the few apps
and how they got built.
Right.
Because you're about to sort of start
scaling, things in a much more.
I'll call a generalized way
where as a developer,
you can start seeing how to build it.
I mean, one of the best things,
that we talked about
was that Stanford demo, right?
Stanford Medicine, think about it. Right.
Something high stakes,
like a tumor board meeting.
How do you use AI to have better
tumor board meetings?
That's a real thing
that one can go to work on.
In order to make that the case, though,
you really have to get data from pathology
from, you know, multiple labs from PubMed
and all getting orchestrated
by multiple agents.
Right.
And then have it show up where users are.
In that case, it was teams.
If you're a teacher who goes to a tumor
board meeting and then wants to go to a,
you know, class as a teaching, doctor,
you want to be able to turn that
into PowerPoints.
And that type of orchestration
is what you want to be able to build.
And I feel to do that,
you got to build up a real stack
right where every layer is open.
It composes.
There are standards that protocols,
and I feel like they're finally there.
And so what is exciting to me
is to have the stack from sort of,
Microsoft 365 Copilot to Foundry, all compose,
with some of these things like NL web
and MCP to create this agentic web.
In some sense, I feel like
even the original ethos of the web,
maybe we can rediscover
which is the true openness.
Yeah.
And it sort of seems like Microsoft's
trying to build this all in one UI,
where you can manage
fleets of agents on one spot.
Is the goal
a world where every knowledge worker
effectively becomes this agent manager
instead of just a knowledge worker?
Yeah, it's it's a metaphor.
I think it that makes sense, right?
When we say we are definitely trying to
build a scaffolding for the AI age, right?
Just like, say, back in the day,
we built teams, right?
You remember?
Or even back in the day.
We built outlook
right before outlook came together.
Calendaring was a separate
app, contacts was a separate app
and email was a separate app.
And so then we said, oh,
maybe we should build it all together.
And outlook was born.
And then teams or meetings was somewhere
else, channels or somewhere else.
And then chat was somewhere else.
And we said, hey,
let's bring that together.
So some, you know, I mean always there's
going to be a need for a new scaffolding.
And in our case, with what I describe
as a UI for AI is you say, well,
let's bring chat, let's even bring search.
And then
our agents and things like notebooks
and so on, all together in one interface.
And that's what we're doing with the M365
Copilot and teams is essentially
the multiplayer version of it.
But it's not the only I'll call it
UI for AI.
There will be many other places
and many other developers will build them.
Right.
You could say the UI for AI for
developers is get up.
UI for AI for some scientist will be,
you know,
what we talked about in our discovery
or some third party application.
So I think there's going to be
a lot more richness on the UI layer
where people will build
different modalities
for different workflows
and different needs.
But the interesting thing
is the underlying capability, right
where you have, hey, you have data,
you have multiple models,
you have these agent orchestration layers,
you have these reasoning models
now that are capable of taking intents
and decomposing it into multiple calls
to multiple models.
That's I think, the exciting thing.
You're the world of knowledge.
Work is just changing so fast
and surely with
any tech revolution
there will be some job displacement.
What advice
would you give to knowledge workers.
So that they effectively
become these agent managers
instead of agent replacement?
Yeah,
I think it's a good way to phrase it,
because I think it's sort
of always helpful for us to separate out,
the knowledge work
go from the knowledge work of today.
Because if you think about it, right,
if you're an alien intelligence had come
to, and seen the world,
you know, at, at, let's say, at work,
even early 80s, and they said, oh, well,
there's a typist pool.
There is a slide pool
or a slide making pool.
And then if they came back,
today, they'll say, oh,
wow, all of humanity is a typist pool.
Because everyone gets up in the morning
and with the two thumbs or,
with multiple fingers are all typing.
But we are doing knowledge work.
It's being abstracted. Right.
So therefore, I think the levels of
abstraction, whether it's managing agents,
if I look at even the simple, simple
workflow from when I joined Microsoft
in 92 to now, if I had if, say, a
somebody had to get prepped for
a, let's say, a customer visit, you know,
you would sort of go to the account team.
The account team would write up a report,
the report would show up in the email
that would get loaded into one note,
and I would read it.
In fact, that was pretty much the sort of,
you know,
I was preparing for most of my career.
Those reports and then eventually,
you know, reading those reports
a lot in the last even 45 months,
thanks to these
things like reasoning models
like researcher, it's completely inverted.
I just go prompt myself, hey, I'm meeting
with the CEO of XYZ Corporation.
Pull all the stuff I need to know.
It pulls from the web.
It pulls from my emails, my documents.
Most importantly my CRM system,
my supply chain system.
Because most of these folks
are both customers and partners of ours.
Gives me one comprehensive report
and then I share it with the accounting.
Right. So think about it.
The workflow is inverted.
So you could say yeah,
I as a CEO quote unquote, I'm
doing more knowledge work
than I was doing, quite frankly.
I am more employable today
because I feel more empowered.
I feel that I can get to information
faster, collaborate
with my colleagues in the company.
So I do feel the best thing that can
happen is diffusion in this phase.
I think any knowledge worker,
whether you're in software, whether you're
in just horizontal knowledge
work, in finance and sales or in science,
use the tools, change the work.
Have you have the agency
to change your work artifacts,
the workflow around you?
And of course, you know, I'm clear eyed
that there is going to be displacement.
And so therefore, the best defense against
that is skilling reskilling.
And it starts by using tools versus,
not using them.
And developers
arguably have seen the biggest shift
to their workflows
with the rise of AI tools.
And now agents and GitHub new Copilot
coding engine is just another example
of another tool that's, you know,
effectively changing the developer work
workflow so much.
You've actually seen recently said
that Microsoft is sharing
30% of all new code with AI.
I'm curious what what
you think the world will look like
when 90 or 95% of all code is generated?
AI yeah, it's
a couple of different things, you know.
One is you got to remember,
like when I look at the amount of deficit
we have, right.
If I sort of looked at, let's call what
people say is tech debt or it debt, right.
Which is if you look around the world
and say the number of projects
that are still unfinished,
the reality is we need a lot more software
development, in order to be able
to really reach, the goal
of being able to work down that deficit.
So you start there. We have a problem.
That is, we don't have all of the software
development capability
and supply in order to meet the demand.
Then you say in that context, that's
why the all these form factors, right.
Even code completions super helpful.
We always had intellisense,
but we now just have better intelligence
that works with code completions.
Or I can highlight a bunch of code
and have it explain it to me
and it'll draw a diagram.
You and yesterday I like took some code
and sort of just highlighted and said,
just give it to me as a flowchart,
like just that simple thing I just
because I do better with visual stuff.
Then you know agents right.
Where I can assign
synchronously some tasks.
So multi file edits,
the full repo changes that I want done.
Right.
So that's all as an individual developer
I can stay in the flow.
I can use these tools
then to be able to today the launch of
the coding agent is pretty cool
because you know like as I said, like
even for me and it's no longer sufficient
to for me to just file bugs.
I got to get involved in
even fixing bugs, right?
To the,
I mean, a programmer that I can work with.
And of course, remember, you know,
ultimately the human is in the loop.
I think we overstate the autonomy
here, right?
Because even before it does any CI CD
thing, it comes back for a human review.
Right.
And it can be, you know, something that
you can even automate with another agent.
But ultimately, there is a workflow here
where people inside of a development
organization are going to work with
these AI agents to essentially work down
the deficit we have.
That's the world I sort of see, more
so than anything else.
Copilot fine tuning was another
really interesting announcement,
giving enterprise
the ability to unlock, you know, their,
their own data and fine tune their own
code parts with it is a major unlock.
I'm curious where you think these
domain specific agents will really excel,
and is there any types of proprietary data
that will give companies
a real advantage over
just like generic Copilot?
Yeah, it's a it's
a super important question, right?
I mean, in some sense, what is the form,
going forward and what is that edge?
The knowledge edge of a form
is the real question.
And that's why I think I'm really excited
about this. Copilot.
Fine tuning,
because the idea is to be able to take
what you have is a form,
which is your knowledge, your data,
and use it to essentially tune,
the copilot system.
But here's the interesting thing, right?
You asked, which is
what's the sustainable advantage here?
And the sustainable advantage
is to get a new sample
to then use these reasoning models
with your data
to then
be able to do RL in the real world.
Right?
So which is the reward function
from the market, reinforcing
the application of your knowledge
to fine tuning the new sample.
Right. That's the virtuous cycle.
So the world keeps getting better
in terms of its model capability.
Forms are about taking that.
That's ultimately a commodity
that you bring into the firm.
You then because of all the knowledge work
you do internally and the data you have,
fine tune it, put out the output
into the world, get the signal.
It could be a customer thumbs up.
It could be marketplace thumbs up,
whatever.
That's the reinforcement. Reward.
And then you go back.
And that I think, is sort of
the new theory of the form in my sort of,
you know, sense of how one needs to go
and you really are going
to have to perfect that loop.
You've led Microsoft through multiple tech
transformations.
What advice would you give to companies
trying to restructure around this
agent era?
you know, with in in tech companies
in particular, in Microsoft in particular,
because remember at Microsoft
we are not like there's one trick company.
In other words, at some level
the hardest thing for us is
being adjusting.
But when I came to Microsoft,
you know, at that time, it is unclear,
like our existential competitor
was Novell.
And so over the years, Microsoft
has had to learn in the hard way.
Sometimes we've gotten it right,
sometimes we've gotten it wrong.
How do I fundamentally change three things
how we work,
what we work on, and how we go to market.
Right.
And that muscle of fundamentally
reinventing the production function
simultaneously with the product
and the innovation,
as well as the go to market
in the business model is a hard thing.
It's a harsh thing,
because in some sense, I wish sometimes
I worked on one product
that lasts, you know, multiple decades.
For us, it's not been the case.
Even something as big a hit as windows,
you know, stopped growing at some point.
And so therefore, it means it meant that
we had to build other businesses.
But I think ultimately it comes down
to culture and capability building.
That allows you
to take more shots on goal.
And that,
I think, is what one needs to do as
any one of us faced with these shifts,
if you have a stable business.
Fantastic.
Then this is tailwind.
You can you can take
and get more leverage out of it.
If you have a business that's in decline,
you can then use this as an opportunity
to reinvent yourself.
but ultimately it comes down
to this culture capability and then hunt
for new concepts that I think,
is what you need to practice.
You can't like.
One of the things I think a lot about is,
you be all like, I do this as well.
We all sort of look at the,
you know, the shining company of the era.
The reality is, case studies don't help.
You have to do it yourself right now.
Somebody said to me once, which is you
don't get fit by watching others
go to the gym. You have to go to the gym.
And that, I think, is what this change is
all about, right?
It's not about admiring someone else.
But it's about really doing the hard yards
yourself.
I want to touch on upskilling
kind of from the top down.
So from my perspective, my company,
we work with a lot of different
enterprises, kind of consulting them
on their strategy and what we've seen
is that there's a lack of personalization
in education.
For example, like the tools and workflows
a marketer might use
are different than a developer
or someone in Customer Success.
So I'm curious
how Microsoft is kind of educating
their employees from the top down on,
on this sort of personalized education.
It's a great point.
So one of the things that we're
emphasizing is getting the tools in.
Right.
Because if you look back
even like one of the things
I'm heavily influenced by
is how PCs became standard issue.
Right?
Is it fascinating to study
even how PCs penetrated the enterprise?
First, you know, someone in legal said,
wow, this is great to write contracts up
because I need word,
you know, with all of its footnotes
and what have you finance
obviously loved Excel, right?
Because, wow,
it can help me do models and so on.
But then it turned out
that people don't work in their silos.
They work in teams.
And so then at some point,
like even the way we did forecast
back, you know, pre PC,
I you know basically faxes went around.
Somebody did an interoffice memo.
And then eventually, you know,
you got to a forecast where,
you know, once the PC became
standard issue,
you just took an Excel spreadsheet,
entered some numbers, sent an email,
all your area leads entered numbers,
and you had a forecast.
It changed the work.
The work artifact in the workflow.
And it happened
not by going to a training class.
It actually happened by diffusion
of the general purpose tool.
In that case, PC in an office.
So a little bit of sort of what I'm seeing
even inside of Microsoft,
whether it's with GitHub Copilot
or whether it's with the M365 copilot
or anywhere else, it's
just the diffusion of the tools.
I'll just give you,
you know, one of the best examples
at Microsoft was I was talking
to an engineer in our networking.
I went right.
I mean, I was talking about, man,
the AI when is growing like crazy.
The number of fiber operators we work with
is like some, you know, insane number.
And by the way,
all of the DevOps on it, right.
You know, if there's a fiber cut
somewhere, it's all a manual, right?
Literally
it is emails and calls and so on.
So she just said, okay,
I can't deal with this.
I have to really automate this
because otherwise, you know,
all of Microsoft
will be just working on DevOps of fiber.
And so she just built an agent
and in fact, a multi-agent orchestrator.
Right.
And by the way, she just did this
using some of the low-code,
no code and the foundry tools. Right.
That ability to empower people,
with tools
and agency to go
and look for the workflow closest to them,
that I think is what needs to happen,
just like how we were able to use,
you know,
I think I always say
Excel is the greatest programing,
most ubiquitous
programing tool on the world.
And all of us learned how to program
in Excel, essentially.
And that's the thing
that I think is going to happen again.
I know we don't have much time here,
but I want to quickly touch on proactive
agents.
So behind the scenes,
we actually got a demo of like on device
proactive agent working on the Copilot
plus PCs where, this agent
essentially opened up, outlook
and summarize email without an internet.
But that's just one example.
Are there any examples that you have
that you're really excited for?
Yeah.
So I think that
if I look at the continuum, right,
so I, I'm really looking for in some sense
I'm a big fan of this Mark Weiser quote
about ubiquitous computing, right,
where technology is powerful
enough to disappear. Right.
So therefore, to some degree,
the march of natural user interface
and so on is about doing all the things
that I intend to be done,
with the least amount of,
I would say friction.
Right.
So that's why I think
when I want, like, interpret
my intent and plan and get it done. Right.
So that's where I think some of these
proactive agent stuff comes in.
And I
want to
be in control though, like, for example,
that's why I think the, the cool agents,
for example, the computer use agents
have to sort of get to a point,
one that can't be fast
and better, and more reliable.
But the more importantly, they have to be
changed as part of some intent, of mine.
Right.
It's not like I'm going to go give task.
Task, task tasks.
I'm going to have a high level intent,
and then someone's going off
and doing a bunch of work
and I can inspect.
So that's why I think like this GitHub,
you know, coding agent, the session log,
it's pretty cool.
Like I go back after having a sign.
It's like I'm watching the session log
with all the draft commits.
Right?
So that I think is the balance. Right.
So in an interesting way, we talk about
the proactive agent and a session log.
And that way
then it's sort of more transparency of it.
And then when you invoke multiple of them
you are able
to still track effectively
what's happening.
One last question for you.
This is something that recently
went viral.
About two months ago,
you said you mentioned
that AGI is just some nonsensical
benchmark hacking,
and the true value of AI is global
economic growth.
Where do you see agents
having the most value in that regard?
First, it's a great one.
I mean, to me, take health care.
What is it, 19-20% of our, GDP in
the United States is in health care.
A lot of that cost the inefficiency.
If you talk to any of our providers,
is all in the workflow, right?
They're working so hard to provide
unbelievable care, except sort of,
you know, and they're using
all these digital systems,
but they're really not able to,
tame the complexity and reduce the cost.
And so if there is going to be one place
where I would love
to love to see that productivity gain,
would be like that,
you know, that multi-agent orchestrator
for health care that we just launched,
used by Stanford become ubiquitous.
And there are stories
that people are saying, oh wow, this is
been the biggest thing that, you know,
every provider is able to provide
better health care at lower cost. Right?
So something like that has to happen
because my only comment
there was not about any sort of shot
on any great AI research.
It is more,
I think we as a society to celebrate
tech companies far too much versus
the impact of technology.
Quite honestly,
if there was a more balanced way to talk
about sort of not the tech industry,
but the use of technology, right.
That's why even the, you know, copilot
being an end to end,
think about the decades
all of us have spent saying,
give me a one tech intervention
that makes a damn difference in education,
right?
Finally,
you have real statistical evidence,
thanks to that world Bank study in Nigeria
that,
you know, you give people copilot their
or any other agent.
It doesn't matter. Something changes.
That's the story to me, right?
That's why I joined the tech industry.
I mean, there is a very different time.
And suddenly it became like, you know,
the place we were celebrating ourselves.
And I just hate it.
I just want to get to a place
where we are talking about the technology
being used
and when the rest of the industry across
the globe is being celebrated
because they use technology
to do something magical for all of us,
that would be the day.
Okay, well,
I think that's all the time we have.
Thank you so much again for doing this
and congrats on the great keynote.
thank you so much. It's
such a pleasure. Great. Thank you.